Guide to the Lee McGee Street Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Lee McGee Street Papers
1968-2010
RG 229
Yale University Divinity School Library
3.5
(8 boxes)
This collection is comprised of writings, correspondence, news clippings, and photographs documenting the life and work of Eleanor "Lee" McGee, including her ordination to the Episcopal priesthood on September 7, 1975. Lee McGee was one of the first women ordained to the priesthood of the Episcopal Church and an early female faculty member at Yale Divinity School, serving from 1987 to 1997 as Squire Professor of Pastoral Counseling. Her career spans a variety of work in college chaplaincy, parish ministry, teaching social work, psychotherapy, consulting and parenthood. This collection provides valuable documentation of the changing role of women in the church.
McGee, Lee
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Lee McGee Street, 2011
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
1943 Aug 24 Eleanor Lee Hofmann was born in Baltimore, Maryland.
1965 Graduated with B.A, Magna Cum Laude, from Maryland State College and entered Yale Divinity School
1967 Struck by rare eye disease of genetic origin, which rendered her permanently legally blind
1968 Married the Rev. Kyle M. McGee; the McGees had two sons
1969 Graduated from Yale Divinity School with a Master of Arts in Religion. Spent one year at University of Edinburgh.
1969 Moved with family to Washington, D.C. where she became a chaplain at American University.
1972-1980 First female chaplain and assistant director of Campus Ministry at American University's multi-denominational Kay Spiritual Life Center.
1973 Ordained a Deacon in the Episcopal Church, in the Diocese of Washington
1975 Irregularly ordained to the Priesthood of the Episcopal Church, by the Right Rev. George Barrett, at St. Stephen and The Incarnation Church in Washington, D.C.
1977 McGee's ordination was "regularized" by Bishop Creighton following the September 16, 1976 vote by the General Convention which determined that ordination to the order of bishop, priest and deacon "shall be equally applicable to men and women".
1980 Completed a clinical Masters of Social Work at Catholic University in Washington, D.C.
1981 Moved with her family to Hartford, CT, where she worked as a priest and social worker with the chronically mentally ill, at soup kitchens and shelters
1982 Began teaching preaching part time at Yale Divinity School
1987-1997 Served as the Roger J. Squire Chair in Pastoral Counseling, Yale Divinity School.
1993 Marriage to the Rev. Kyle McGee ended
1994 The Eleanor Lee McGee and Gaylord Brewster Noyce Endowment in Pastoral Ministries was established at Yale Divinity School through generous gifts from the estates of Almon Elizur Hall and Amy Ericson Hall. The Endowment honors two Divinity faculty members who have made noteworthy contributions to student preparation for pastoral ministries.
1996 Published Wrestling with the Patriarchs: Retrieving Women's Voices in Preaching with Thomas H. Troeger, Abingdon Press
1997- After retirement from YDS, lectured in England and the U.S. and led conferences on preaching, discernment, and Christian spirituality
1999 Eleanor Lee McGee Prize was established by the Berkeley Divinity School Graduate Society
2000 Married the Rev. C. Parke Street '60 B.D
2008 Returned to New Haven with her husband after 10 years on a ranch in Colorado.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains valuable materials collected by Lee McGee Street documenting her ordination to the Episcopal priesthood, as well as writings and correspondence regarding the role of women in the church.
Series I, Writings and Interviews is comprised of manuscripts, notes, articles, and sermons written by Lee McGee, as well as interviews with her, including audiotapes of an interview conducted for the Women's History Project at Yale Divinity School.
Series II, Ordination Documentation contains writings and correspondence regarding Lee McGee's decision to seek ordination, the ordination ceremony, and the events that took place following the "irregular" ordination. The Files by Person are comprised of correspondence, writings, and news clippings pertaining to individuals who were involved with the ordination, including the bishop who performed the ceremony and some of the other women who were ordained at the same time as Lee McGee. The files arranged alphabetically. There is an extensive collection of news clippings describing the events leading up to the ordination, the ordination ceremony, and subsequent events related to the role of women in the church.
Series III, Writings by Others includes collected manuscripts, addresses, lectures, and sermons primarily about the ordination of women to the priesthood.
Series IV, Conferences contains collected materials from conferences attended by Lee McGee Street.
Series V, Collected Publications includes newsletters, periodicals, and articles pertaining to the role of women in church leadership.
Series VI, Photographs and Memorabilia contains photographs and memorabilia. Of special interest is a group of photographs documenting the Lee McGee's ordination on September 7, 1975 at St. Stephen and the Incarnation Episcopal Church.
Arrangement
I. Writings and Interviews of Lee McGee Street, 1973-2010
II. Ordination Documentation, 1970-2010
III. Writings by Others, 1970-2011
IV. Conferences, 1973-2006
V. Collected Publications, 1971-1992
VI. Photographs and Memorabilia, 1971-1999
Ordination of women -- Episcopal Church; Women in the Episcopal Church; McGee, Lee
- Writings and Interviews of Lee McGee Street, 1973-2010; Series I
  - Writings and Notes
    - Essay on the Ordination of the Philadelphia Eleven, ca.1975 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "Lee McGee, Diocese of Washington." Our Call, edited by Frances Trott., 1973 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Notes and manuscripts regarding Ordination, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Notes regarding Ordination, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Notes on sex roles, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Inclusive language education and prayers (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Articles
    - Viewpoint. American University Report; A.A. for the Woman; Is A.A. for You?; Young People and A.A.; The Characteristics of a Helping Relationship; Outline: Eating Disorders/Substance Abuse; The Family Genogram, 1968-1979 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "Women and the Preaching Ministry." Yale Divinity School Reflection., 1983 Nov (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Sermons
    - Ordination of Flora A. Keshgegian to the Diaconate, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Mark 8:34-38, St. John's Church, Norwood Parish, Bethesda-Chevy Chase, Maryland, 1976 Feb8 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Untitled, St. Stephen and the Incarnation Easter Service, 1978 Apr 16 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Ordination of Martha Bateman-Cooper to the Diaconate, 1978 May 4 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - "New Beginnings", 1978 Sep 3 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Untitled, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - "Amos 7", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - "Have You Ever Thought About the Kind of Woman Pictured in the New Testament?" (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - "Let Us Answer Our Call!", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - "Mark 8:27-38", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - "Of Women in the Gospels Take on a New Significance", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Sermon regarding Ordination, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Untitled, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 21-24)
    - Partial Sermons, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Sermon Notes, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 26-28)
  - Interviews
    - "Need for Cooperation in the Priesthood: An Interview with Rev. Lee McGee." New Age News, 1976 Mar (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - "Women Priests: Ten Years Later." Berkeley Divinity School at Yale Newsletter, 1984 Nov (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Yale Divinity School - Women's History Project, Interview of Rev. Lee McGee regarding Ordination and Teaching. Interviewed by Joyce Trickett, Interview transcribed by Dawn Detgen (includes audiotapes of the interview), 1993 Apr 21 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - "The Right to Ordination." Diocese of Connecticut News, 2001 Aug-Sep (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Interview with Lee McGee, 2010 Sep 29 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Ordination Documentation, 1970-2010; Series II
  - Lee McGee
    - Woman Chaplain: Ray of Light for AU Coeds. The AU Report, 1972 Sep-Oct (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Ordination Application and Examination, 1972-1974 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Legal Documents and Correspondence, 1974-1976 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Committee for the Ordination of Women, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Policy Statements, Open Letters, and Writings and Notes by Lee McGee, 1974-1976 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Ordination Announcement by Phyllis Edwards, Eleanor Lee McGee, Alison Palmer, Betty Rosenberg, and Diane Tickell, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - A Statement of Intention by the Rt. Rev. George W. Barrett; Decision to Ordain; Summary of Remarks following Ordination, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Ordination Program and Invitation, 1975 Sep 7 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Ordination Sermon, St. Stephen's and the Incarnation, 1975 Sep 7 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Certificate - Oath of Conformity, Episcopal Church, Alison Palmer, Betty Rosenberg, Lee McGee (notarized copy), 1975 Sep 7 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Address on the Canonical Aspects of the Ordination of Women by Henry H. Rightor, 1975 Sep (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Report of the Council of Advice, 1975 Sep 22 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Yale Divinity School Eucharistic Fast, 1976 Feb 27 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Thoughts on Regularization, George W. Barrett, Daniel Corrigan, Robert L. DeWitt, 1976 Oct 15 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Conferring of the Sacred Order of Priest in the Service of Ordination and Consecration for Lee McGee and Betty Rosenberg, 1977 Jan 8 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Dress Guidelines for Clergy Women Serving in the Anglo-Catholic Parish of the Episcopal Church, ca.1975 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Ordination Collected Material, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Files by Person
    - Anderson, Vienna, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Barrett, Rt. Rev. George W. (Bishop), 1975-2000 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Cheek, Alison, 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Creighton, Bishop William F., 1972-1976 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Dewitt, Bishop Robert Lionne, 1975, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Fuller, Georgia Whippo, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Hewitt, Emily Clark, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Heyward, Carter, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Hiatt, Suzanne Radley, 1973-2002 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Hwang, Rev. Jane, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Palmer, Alison. Questionnaire Regarding the Status of Women Deacons Seeking Ordination to the Episcopal Priesthood, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Palmer, Alison. Correspondence, 1975-1978, 2004-2008 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Palmer, Alison, 1971-1977 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Palmer, Alison, 2010 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Rich, Susan, 1978 May (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Rosenberg, Elizabeth Powell, 1973-1975 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Russell, Letty Mandeville, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Schiess, Betty, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Stodghill, Marion Whitbread, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Swanson, Katrina, 1973-2005 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Tickell, Diane, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Walker, Rt. Rev. John T., 1977 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Wendt, Rev. William A., 1975 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Wendt, Rev. William A., 1975-2001 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Files by Institution
    - Episcopal Divinity School, Cambridge, Massachusetts, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Kay Spiritual Life Center, American University, 1972-1978 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Levine Museum of the New South, Correspondence re Women in Religion Program, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - St. Stephen and the Incarnation Episcopal Church (includes copies of the Newsletter Bread), 1970-1991 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - St. Stephen and the Incarnation Episcopal Church, 1999-2001 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence
    - Ordination Correspondence, 1973-1974 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Ordination Correspondence, 1975 Jan-Aug (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Ordination Correspondence, 1975 Sep (Box 4, Folder 6-7)
    - Ordination Correspondence, 1975 Oct (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Ordination Correspondence, 1975 Nov-Dec (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Ordination Correspondence, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Ordination Correspondence, 1977-1978 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Ordination Correspondence (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - General Correspondence, 1971-2006 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Organizations
    - Christian Parity Goup, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Minnesota Committee for Women's Ordination NOW, 1975-1976 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - National Committees for Women's Ordination to the Priesthood and Episcopacy (various committees), 1973-1975 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - National Organization for Women (NOW), 1974-1976 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Women's Ordination Now (WON), 1975-1976 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Anniversary Celebrations
    - 10th Anniversary of the Ordination of Women Priests (includes news clippings), 1984 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - 10th Anniversary of the Irregular Ordination of Four Women Priests at St. Stephen and the Incarnation, 1985 Sep 8 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - 20th Anniversary of the Ordination of Women to the Priesthood in the Episcopal Church, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Witness Awards (includes audiotape), 1994 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - 25th Anniversary of the Ordination of Women to the Priesthood in the Episcopal Church, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Episcopal Women's History Project, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - News Clippings
    - News Clippings, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - News Clippings, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - News Clippings, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Religious News Service, 1975-1977 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - News Clippings, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - News Clippings, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - News Clippings, 1978-1979 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - News Clippings, 1981-1987 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - News Clippings re Barbara Harris, First Woman Bishop in the Anglican Communion, 1988-1989 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - News Clipiings, 1994-1999 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - News Clippings, 2001-2006 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - News Clippings, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Writing by Others, 1970-2011; Series III
  - Manuscripts, Lectures, and Addresses
    - Brakeman, Lyn G. "Becoming a Woman Priest." Chapter19, Forgive Us Our Debts (re Lee McGee), 2011 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Boyd, Jeff. Chapter 9. "The Soul of a Lutheran", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Cromey, Robert W. "The Ordination Circus", 1975 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - DeWitt, Robert L. "One Pilgrim's Progress", Kellogg Lecture, 1985 May 21 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Rightor, Henry Haskell. "The Existing Canonical Authority for Women's Ordination", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Stewart, Rt. Rev. Alexander Doig." Seventh Annual Address of the Bishop for the 75th Annual Meeting of the Convention of the Diocese of Western Massachusetts", 1976 Nov 5 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Swidler, Leonard. "Jesus was a Feminist", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Sermons and Prayers
    - Archbishop of Canterbury's Sermon at York Minster, General Synod July Group Sessions, 2008 Jul 6 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Bishop George Barrett Sermon Audiotape. 35th Anniversary as Bishop, Trinity Episcopal Church, Santa Barbara, Califonia, 1998 May 10 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Ridgely, Rev. Benjamin J. "Something Went Wrong", 1975 Sep 7 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Street, Rev. C. Parke. "Pentecost XVI and Day of Illegal Ordination to the Priesthood of Women Deacons. St. Margaret's Church, Washington, D.C.", 1975 Sep 7 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Way, Rev. Pegg. "You are not my God, Jehovah", 1970 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Sermons re Ordination, authors unidentified, 1975, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Collected Sermons, 1973-1978, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Collected Prayers, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Prayers Services, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 23)
- Conferences, 1973-2006; Series IV
  - Covenant Community, 1973-1976 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Diocesan Task Force on Women, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Conference for Episcopal Woman Seminarians, Virginia Theological Seminary, 1973 Mar 30-31 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Episcopal Women's Caucus, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Experimental Worship Group Retreat, Planning Notes and Collected materials re the retreat, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - General Convention of the Episcopal Church, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - National Organizing Conference for the Ordination of Women to the Priesthood and Episcopate, 1974 Oct 24-26 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Women and Ordination in the Christian Churches: International Perspectives, Lincoln Theological Institute, University of Manchester, 2006 Jul 12-14 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Women Exploring Theology, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Women in Ministry: The Ministry of Women, First Annual Barrett Conference, 2001 May 1-4 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Women Proclaiming: Research, Issues and Resources, 1995 Mar 13-17 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Women's Ordination Conference, 1977 Jun 27 (Box 7, Folder 12)
- Collected Publications, 1971-1992; Series V
  - Newsletters and Periodicals
    - De-Liberation, 1974-1976 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Faith at Work, 1974 Oct (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - The Feminist Times, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Genesis-3: Philadelphia Task Force on Women in Religion, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Post American, 1974 Aug-Sep, 1975 May (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Responses: United Methodist Women, 1972 Jul-Aug (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Washington Diocese, 1975, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - The Witness, 1984 Aug (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - The Witness, 1984 Sep (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - The Witness Special Issue - Daughters of Prophecy: Episcopal Women Priests 10th Anniversary, 1974-1984 (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - Women Deacons Newsletter, 1975 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Yale Divinity School Reflection, 1976 Nov, 1985 Jan (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Collected Publications, 1975-1976 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Articles
    - Articles regarding the ordination of women, 1972-1975 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Women in the church collected material, 1972-1992 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Articles regarding women's rights and feminism, 1970-1973 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - "The Power of Women and the Subversion of the Community" (collection of articles), 1972 (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Photographs and Memorabilia, 1971-1999; Series VI
  - Photographs
    - Lee McGee, ca.1975 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Ordination at St. Stephen and the Incarnation Episcopal Church, 1975 Sep 7 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Farewell Picnic, 1981 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Lee McGee performing a baptism, St. Stephen's Church, Bloomfield, 1984 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Alison Cheek, Carter Heyward, Suzanne Hiatt, Alla Bozarth Campbell, Lee McGee in Philadelphia, 1984 Jul 29 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Guide dog, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Memorabilia
    - Collected Programs, 1971-1994 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Memorabilia, 1999, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Memos, Notes, and Messages (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Miscellaneous, including information about Eleanor Lee McGee and Gaylord Brewster Noyce Endowment in Pastoral Mnistries, 1975, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 17)